<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chronicles of a Junior Dev</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:56:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 16:56:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introducing the Chronicles</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To write, you have to want something to survive you.” -Elena Ferrante&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;August marks the one year anniversary of my first &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; post. It took me &lt;em&gt;weeks&lt;/em&gt; to work up the guts to publicly share my writing. Ever since my elementary school days, I&amp;#39;ve been praised for my way with words. I floated through high school and college on a sea of A&amp;#39;s in humanities courses. So what held me back from pressing &amp;quot;publish&amp;quot;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear that my words would be for naught made me nervous. Everything else I&amp;#39;d ever written had a clear-cut audience – like a journal entry or a professor-assigned exegesis – but forecasting whether my &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ladies-storm-hackathons/the-gender-gap-as-told-by-data-71dfce420519&quot;&gt;first blog post&lt;/a&gt; would be of any help was daunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I&amp;#39;ve learned and then reaffirmed that writing is as much for others as it is for me. &lt;strong&gt;I like my writing best when it has the dual purpose of helping me self-reflect and helping others learn something new&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m about to embark upon a new phase of my life: my first full-time job. I believe that any big change in one&amp;#39;s life demands self-reflection, and, for me, that means writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m starting &lt;strong&gt;Chronicles of a Junior Dev&lt;/strong&gt;. Welcome! 👋&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chronicles of a Junior Dev will be a biweekly log of experiences, mishaps, and takeways from my first year as a software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I believe that beginners — like me, a new grad engineer — share the best advice because they remember exactly what it’s like to start from the bottom.&lt;/strong&gt; I’ll use Chronicles of a Junior Dev as a place to document my on-the-job growth for my own sake and, most importantly, in the hopes that budding engineers can learn from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So join me in my journey from software engineering novice to... well, who knows? Expect new installments in this nail-biter of a life story on every other Monday. 🙀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To be updated about new posts in the Chronicles of a Junior Dev saga, follow me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alainakafkes&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/07/introduction.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/08/07/introduction.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
